Finding Aid for Gladys Kapenga papers, ca. 1960-ca. 2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gladys Kapenga papers circa 1960-2010, 1985-2007
Kapenga, Gladys
8 linear feet
2012045 Aa 2
Gladys Kapenga was heavily involved with the United Church of Christ and Church Women United in Michigan. This collection documents both organizations and is particularly strong in its coverage of women’s organizations in the United Church of Christ. The collection includes administrative files for Burlingame Congregational Church, UCC Women of Michigan, the UCC Michigan Conference, the Grand West Association, and Church Women United.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Gladys Kapenga (donor no. 10723 ) in February 2012.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Gladys Gray was born on July 14, 1927 in Michigan. She married John Kapenga on August 31, 1946 at Burlingame Congregational Church, where they were both members. They had three children together.
Kapenga worked at Michigan Bell and AT&T for 40 years, before retiring in 1989. Upon her retirement, Kapenga took on a growing leadership role in the religious community in Michigan, particularly within the United Church of Christ (UCC). She served as President of the Women's Fellowship at Burlingame Congregational, Secretary for the UCC Women of Grand Rapids Area, and President of the UCC Women of Michigan. She was also on the Board of Directors for the Michigan Conference of the United Church of Christ and was Moderator of the Grand West Association. She was named a UCC Laywoman of the Year in 1995.
Outside of the United Church of Christ, Kapenga was actively involved in Church Women United (CWU) as the Vice President of Church Women United of Michigan and President of Church Women United Greater Grand Rapids Unit. She was named a CWU Valiant Woman in 1996. Church Women United was founded in 1941 as a national volunteer Christian ecumenical women's organization composed of at least 26 different religious denominations. CWU was intended to bring together women of diverse races, cultures, and traditions.
The Gladys Kapenga collection contains papers related to Church Women United, Burlingame Congregational Church, and the United Church of Christ in Michigan. The collection has been organized in nine series: United Church of Christ (UCC); Church Women United; Committee Files; Events and Meetings; Outreach and Ministry; Publications and Newsletters; Topical Files; Miscellaneous Files; and Personal Files.
Subjects:
Burlingame Congregational United Church of Christ (Wyoming, Mich.); Church Women United--Michigan.; United Church of Christ--Michigan.; United Church of Christ. Michigan Conference.; Women--Religious life--Michigan.
- United Church of Christ (UCC)
  The United Church of Christ series contains material relating to Burlingame Congregational Church, UCC Women of Michigan, the Michigan Conference, and the Grand West Association. These files include annual reports, directories, bylaws, and handbooks.
  - General (Box 1)
  - Burlingame Congregational United Church of Christ
    - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - Bylaws (Box 1)
    - Directories (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - History (Box 1)
    - Programs, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Search Committee (Box 1)
    - Women's Fellowship
      - General (Box 1)
      - Directories (Box 1)
  - Global Ministries
    - General (Box 1)
    - Ministries and Mission Interpretation (Box 1)
  - UCC Women of Michigan
    - Annual Meeting (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - Directories, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Manuals (Box 2)
    - Standing Rules and Bylaws (Box 2)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - JCER (Box 2)
  - UCC Michigan Conference
    - General, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Board of Directors (Box 2)
    - Bylaws (Box 2)
    - Conference Connections (Box 2)
    - Directories, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Conference News (Box 2)
  - Grand West Association, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Grand West Association, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Women of the Grand West Association
    - Annual Reports (Box 3)
    - Directories (Box 3)
    - General (Box 3)
  - STEM Licensed Ministry Program (Box 3)
  - Jubilee 2000 (Box 3)
  - JAMRA (Box 3)
  - Synod (Box 3)
- Church Women United
  The Church Women United series contains records relating to the activities of Church Women United in Michigan. This material includes Board of Directors files, annual reports, directories, and handbooks. There is also material relating to the position of Church Women United in relation to various national and international policies.
  - Administrative Binder (Box 3)
  - Administrative Committee (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Board of Directories Meeting and Working Tools (Box 4)
  - Common Council (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
  - Grand Rapids Unit, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Local Units (Box 4)
  - Michigan Ecumenical Forum (Box 4)
  - FAQ (Box 4)
  - Reflections (Box 4)
  - Annual Reports (Box 4)
  - Directories (Box 4)
  - Mailing Lists (Box 4)
  - Articles of Incorporation (Box 4)
  - Treasurer's Reports (Box 4)
  - Financial Statements, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Basic Books, 3 binders; 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Handbooks
    - General (Box 4)
    - Local Unit Handbook (Box 5)
    - Handbook for State Units (Box 5)
    - Operating Handbook (Box 5)
    - Ecumenical Development (Box 5)
    - Information Handbooks and Directories (Box 5)
  - Gifts and Accessories (Box 5)
  - Policies and Positions (Box 5)
  - Valiant Women (Box 5)
  - Other Programs (Box 5)
- Committees
  The Committee Files included information related to Kapenga's involvement in various committees that were part of Church Women United and the United Church of Christ. These committees include Women Leading in Community (LINC) and the Commission on Church and Society in a Modern World. There is also material related to Kapenga's involvement in the United Nations Association.
  - Women Leading in Community (LINC) (Box 5)
  - Commission on Church and Society in Modern World, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Ecumenical Action, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - United Nations Association, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Events and Meetings
  Events and Meetings is composed of records relating to UCC and CWU events attended by Kapenga. The records of the Church Women United Annual State Assembly are particularly strong.
  - Regional Event Planning (Box 5)
  - Gathering, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Assembly (Box 5)
  - United Nations Tour (Box 5)
  - Michigan Conference Annual Meeting (Box 5)
  - Church Women United Annual Meeting (Box 5)
  - Visions and Voices (Box 5)
  - Area Meeting (Box 5)
  - Fall Retreat (Box 5)
  - State Assembly, 1 folder (Box 5)
  - State Assembly, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - East Central Regional Event, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Great Lakes Regional Event (Box 6)
  - Heartland Team Meeting (Box 6)
  - Jubilee 2000 (Box 6)
  - Mid-Quadrennial Gather 1998 (Box 6)
  - Mix In '06 (Box 6)
  - Global Connection: A Bridge Between Cuba and Michigan (Box 6)
  - Human Rights Luncheon (Box 6)
  - Quadrennial Assembly (Box 6)
  - Stewardship University (Box 6)
  - Flyers (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Outreach and Ministry
  Outreach and Ministry contains material documenting both religious and community oriented activities of Church Women United and the United Church of Christ. This series includes files related to the Fellowship of the Least Coin, World Day of Prayer, and training materials distributed by Church Women United.
  - General, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Be a Beacon (Box 6)
  - Installation Service (Box 6)
  - Building a World Fit for Children (Box 6)
  - Fellowship of the Least Coin (Box 6)
  - Sisters of Faith, Rise Up! (Box 6)
  - Women's Mosaic Series (Box 7)
  - World Day of Prayer (Box 7)
  - Worship Programs (Box 7)
- Publications and Newsletters
  The Publications and Newsletters series is primarily composed of newsletters produced by various Church Women United chapters across the country. There are also a variety of flyers distributed by Church Women United.
  - Flyers (Box 7)
  - The Center Report (Box 7)
  - Chat With Us (Louisiana) (Box 7)
  - Massachusetts/Rhode Island Churchwoman (Box 7)
  - Churchwoman (Box 7)
  - A.D. 1981 (Box 7)
  - Indiana Churchwoman (Box 7)
  - Texas Churchwoman (Box 7)
  - Illinois Interpreter (Box 7)
  - Access Connector (Box 7)
  - Equity (Box 7)
  - Churchwoman News (Box 7)
  - Michigan Churchwoman (Box 7)
  - Lamplighter (Box 7)
  - Press Releases (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files are composed of documents related to social and political topics of interest to Kapenga and Church Women United. This series includes material related to the 2000 election, various United Nations policies, and health care.
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - 2000 Election (Box 8)
  - Climate Change (Box 8)
  - AIDS (Box 8)
  - Adopt-a-Minefield (Box 8)
  - Care Giving (Box 8)
  - Convention on the Rights of the Child (Box 8)
  - Global Ministries (Box 8)
  - Greenfield Village (Box 8)
  - Health Care (Box 8)
  - International Criminal Court (Box 8)
  - Iraq (Box 8)
  - Latin America (Box 8)
  - Michigan Civil Rights Initiative (Box 8)
  - Parliamentary Procedure (Box 8)
  - Racism (Box 8)
  - Universal Declaration of Human Rights (Box 8)
  - Human Trafficking (Box 8)
  - UNICEF (Box 8)
  - United Nations (Box 8)
  - Violence Against Women Act (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous Files
  The Miscellaneous Files includes press clippings, correspondence, and files related to the Pilgrim Manor Retirement community.
  - Clippings (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Godfrey-Lee Public Schools Directories (Box 8)
  - Pilgrim Manor, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Personal Files
  Personal Files is composed of material related to Kapenga's personal life. This material includes photographs, calendars, and awards received by Kapenga.
  - Awards, 3 plaques; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Travel (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Photographs, 3 folders (Box 8)